[Music]
my name is doug sheehan i'm one of the
lead gameplay programmers at insomniac
games
and we're here to talk about building
traversal in marvel spider-man
so let's just jump right in so in the
fall of 2014
uh i found out insomniac games was
making a spider-man game and that i was
going to be assigned to bring his
traversal to life
this was not only going to be the
biggest game in insomniac's history but
it was also using a legendary ip that
had
really heavily infested and rabbit hand
fan base
and it had an unrivaled expectation of
quality for anything that we'd ever made
and as someone that as a poor college
student holed up in bookstores and read
spider-man comics
the idea of making spider-man swing was
super exciting
and also at the same time completely and
utterly terrifying
fortunately we had the game's vision
statement as a starting point which was
play like a superhero movie feels
so we kind of set up on our journey too
as the saying goes make you feel like
spider-man
so what does plane like a superhero
movie feels even mean for traversal
well with swinging as our starting point
we decided on a few core beliefs
that would kind of guide the features
development so the first thing we
acknowledged was that we wanted to
target a pretty broad audience
spider-man has a really big worldwide
following and we wanted as many people
as possible to be able to play and enjoy
the game
however we knew that we had the issue
that most gamers don't really have any
muscle memory for swinging
unlike say a third person shooter or a
first person shooter most folks don't
have any brain map for how to make
swinging go and function
so to add to the challenge we start the
game out by chucking you out a window
giving you the control and saying all
right swing time
go so wanting that first moment to feel
just right we knew we had to get the
controls to a point where they were easy
to learn
but hard to master next we wanted
traversal and swinging in particular to
be rooted in physics
this was really vital to give players a
sense of believability that feeling that
they could actually swing through new
york as a superhero that that was really
going to be possible for them
and following that swing lines just had
to attach to in-world geometry no
questions asked
this was extremely important in order to
ground the simulation correctly
but also we were mostly terrified that a
bunch of angry fans would tell us that
we were ruining their childhood if we
didn't do it
so finally we wanted to have a dynamic
camera the look and feel of swinging
needed to be fluid
fast exciting and especially cinematic
we needed a camera that helped translate
all that high-flying acrobatics
and velocity into a really visceral
experience for the player something that
they could just feel in their gut
so today i'm going to show you kind of
how we achieve those core principles by
taking you through the process by which
we created traversal
the biggest key to our success is
iteration for a lot of the elements i'll
show you
not just what we ended up actually
shipping but where we started where we
failed what we learned and how we got
better
and so however knowing when you needed
to improve isn't necessarily always
obvious to you
it came from a steady diet of play
testing and learning how players
interacted with the game and where it
was failing them
this meant we had to stay really
flexible in our execution and always
looking to be greater
so before we can actually swing we have
to have something to attach to
so as stated we wanted swinging to be
accessible and this meant that we needed
to think a bit about attach points from
the player's perspective
namely what is the player actually going
to be responsible for when it comes to
picking an attach point and what is the
system going to be responsible for
and doing to help them so we first
decided that we wanted players really
just thinking about
where they wanted to go rather than
where they were attaching
this removed a pretty significant burden
from the player and let them focus on
additional layers of gameplay
like chasing cars dodging bullets
rockets and the occasional pigeon
the player would communicate their
directional intent with the with the
analog stick and then the system would
take it from there
so our first attempt at finding attach
points was to comb the environment using
an array of raycasts
this was designed to minimize the
required effort from design and
environment and to ensure that we were
actually attaching the geometry
but this presented a number of problems
that we just couldn't overcome at the
end of the day
the biggest issue is that raycasts
simply didn't provide enough resolution
for
us our line lengths would often exceed
50 meters and even with a respectable
density of raycast we were getting these
20 meter gaps at full range
this was enough to not only miss small
objects that we wanted to swing from
like flagpoles and radio towers
but it would completely miss large
sections of buildings entirely
specifically an additional issue we
recognized is that corners were often
the optimal swing points
and raycasts were just really bad at
finding those positions because of the
resolution problem
so a more obvious problem is that
raycasts can't hit things that don't
have collision
this was particularly problematic with
trees in areas like central park
and even if those objects did have a
little bit of collision for the trunk or
something like that
we still weren't going to be able to
find them because of the resolution
issue
and finally as we'll talk about later a
lot of points require some additional
fix up after you find that initial point
doing these adjustments by collision
checks could prove really costly and
a performance hit when processing dozens
of potential attach points
and they still might not really be what
we want
so with those raycasts coming up short
we moved on we decided to use a markup
based approach
by wrapping our buildings in box volumes
that approximate the shape of the
building
we could find those nearby volumes
process them on a face-by-face basis
and then only then perform a final
raycast on that point to get their true
attach point on the geometry
but moving to moving to market provided
a number of advantages
that were absent when using raycasts
first point collection was really fast
by using kind of a cache friendly sphere
database uh that was just our data it
significantly helped with scalability in
terms of being able to have a lot of
markup out in the world and be able to
process it quickly
by using the shape information we
effectively now had infinite resolution
for point placement on each face of the
volume
this allowed us to easily find edges and
corners and never have to worry about
missing smaller objects
and finally by using markup we were able
to afford designers a lot of additional
control over various gameplay aspects
like custom swing parameters and where
you could and couldn't swing so the main
drawback with markup was placement
scalability we had a huge world full of
things that were going to require the
markup and placing all of this by hand
and maintaining it through production as
environment was constantly changing
was going to be an enormous amount of
upkeep and potential bugs so our
solution to that involved a couple of
primary tools
first we had to handle the buildings
fortunately we were using a system
called houdini
to help us generate the geometry for our
environment out of building blocks
this software could also then be
leveraged to analyze that geometry and
procedurally place volumes
to approximate our building shapes for
objects outside of houdini's operation
we deployed our engine's prefab system
this bundled up markup with all of those
objects that we place and every time an
instance was put down it would just
bring the markup in with it so we didn't
have to worry about it
so with our markup now populating the
world we needed to actually do something
kind of useful for it rather than just
stare at it
and at any point the immediate area can
be filled with just hundreds of volumes
that are all potential swing points and
we needed to filter through all that to
find the best one
so in order to pick that final attach
point uh we need to start with a
reasonable reference point as our ideal
position
here we kind of have a top-down view of
our hero surrounded by buildings
and the player influence over point
selection comes from the input on the
left stick
and as stated before we want the player
thinking only about where they're going
not specifically where they're attaching
so the input direction really just kind
of provides a starting point
from that input direction we can then
apply an ideal slope and a line length
to transform the input direction into a
position that represents kind of our
ideal attach point where we would want
to go if we had
you know infinite attach points all over
and moving back to a top-down view
we can then use that position to
generate two more points on each face
the first one is the point that's
closest to a reference point and the
next is a raycast point along our ideal
line direction which is then just
clamped to the
volume bounds so we can then
blend between those two points to get
our output point for any situation
the closest point is most useful when
you want to swing along the face and
swing parallel to it
while the right cast point is most
useful when you're swinging directly at
the object
and then we can just kind of blend
between those based on what your input
is relative to the face normal to get
one that's most appropriate
so now that we have a point we need to
refine it a little bit in order to make
it more effective
our blended point can change the slope
and the line length a lot which can lead
to really long flat lines short and
steep lines
and everything kind of in between so we
really wanted to try and give the player
a more kind of consistent rhythm with
swinging
and that meant that we needed to try and
keep those lines as consistent as
possible
so we wanted to move things around a
little bit to get closer to the ideal
so this is an example of shifting the
attach point up just a little bit in
order to get closer to that ideal slope
which had gotten kind of overly
flattened by the closest point
calculation
by moving more towards this ideal slope
you can see that we prevent the player
from having quite so much
an excessive drop during the swing which
will then make it more consistent as
they go swing to swing and more
predictable
so now that we've generated this field
of points across a whole bunch of markup
faces
and we need to actually decide which one
is going to be our swing point for this
frame
so we do this by scoring each of the
points and taking the best one
our scoring algorithm is then geared to
fulfill that desire of translating that
stick input to a point that moves us in
the desired direction
so our first scoring element is how the
face normal relates to input direction
as i said you're trying to swing
parallel uh to the faces where possible
in this case
and so the input direction means that
the player will be able to swing along
that surface in the direction they
desire
now because corners provide the player
the most control we do try and snap
points uh two edges when they're nearby
so we can then use the best normal
available on that entire sweep of the
corner
to compare against input for our score
calculation we can also give corners a
bonus when we're trying to turn if that
corner is going to help us
make that turn but taking input into
account
we start with the angle between the
input direction and the direction of the
attach point and then we score that
delta
and for range we're looking for points
that match kind of our ideal length and
then it just falls off in either
direction as we deviate from that
and we apply a similar falloff method
for slope as the angle moves away from
our ideal
and once we have all that together we
can do a weighted sum
and the highest score is going to win
so here you can see it all coming
together in game the blue boxes
are our market volumes and you can see a
little bit of debug info about each
point score floating above it
that kind of helps us figure out when we
try to debug
why one point is better than another
point particularly if we didn't want
that to be the case we can go
adjust those weighting values in order
to
tune swinging to make it so that we're
continuing to get the expected point
so now that we have our attach point we
can talk about what happens
when you're actually on the line so as
stated we wanted to have a physics-based
system that we modify the results of so
we're going to start with the physics
and then proceed to kind of mess with
the universe a little bit
so the two basic forces involved in the
pendulum are gravity and tension
as you can see here the tension is a
factor of line length angle
and gravity all in the direction of the
line and it's kind of responsible for
pulling that bob of the pendulum in a
circle around the center of the system
we also break gravity up into its two
component vectors here one parallel to
the line and one perpendicular
the perpendicular portion represents
that kind of restoring force it's a
thing that makes the pendulum oscillate
back and forth
and the parallel portion is what's left
and you'll see in our calculations we
can actually cancel that out with part
of tension to simplify the math a little
bit
which we do here so when actually
calculating this encode we internally
just set the mass to one since we're not
really dealing with a variable mass
system and we can tune gravity how we
want to
and after a bit of simplification we
apply the remaining forces of tension
and perpendicular gravity to our
velocity also just for a little bit more
accuracy we do four iterations each
frame to run the entire thing at about
120 hertz
so when we're talking about how we
wanted swinging to feel the number one
thing that came up was that swings
needed to feel fluid
this led to a couple of rules that drove
uh drove a variety of other elements
within the swing system
first we wanted to avoid slack lines we
wanted to keep the player feeling like
they were swinging
not falling so by keeping the line taut
at all times it gave the player a much
more predictable experience and
prevented kind of bounciness and sudden
change in direction as that as that
slack line goes taut
from a free fall and this led to
the need that once a line is shortened
it generally stays that length
we do look for opportunities to try and
kind of restore lost line length when
possible but doing so too quickly feels
really wrong to people and so we had to
be really careful to do that with
caution
so our first goal or our first goal on
getting a new line is then giving a
player a good experience of just
getting into the swing but the initial
setup poses an immediate challenge
the incoming velocity is almost always
very very different than the velocity
that's going to be tangent to the swing
arc
and we don't want to just snap it
because that's going to feel like a
sudden change in direction and just give
players whiplash
so however we just if we just let the
simulation play out as is
you get something that looks a bit like
this because of our rule that we don't
allow the line to lengthen again the
velocity running into the center of the
swing arc shortens the line up
considerably
and this can result in losing the
entirety of the swings dip as well as
causing a really rapid acceleration in
angular velocity
that's hard for players to react to they
just get shot up in the air without
knowing what happened
so to improve we blend the incoming
velocity towards the tangent direction
of the swing arc a little bit on each
iteration
this helps maintain healthier line
lengths and improves the expected
behavior and the angular velocity
and the player can also now feel a lot
more significant drop on the swing arc
compared to the previous motion path
so now that they're into the swing the
player is going to want to further mess
around with their motion
in order to move themselves around so we
do this with just a simple accelerated
rotation on the total velocity
we scale that turn speed based on your
max we scale that turn speed based on
where you are in the swing arc so you
get more control of the trough
less up at the apexes so you kind of
come to a stall that feels about right
and we can also adjust the turn speed
based on whether you're turning with the
attach point or away from the attach
point
so when it comes to managing speed while
on the line things are going to vary a
lot from swing to swing
the two biggest influences on speed for
any given swing will be the amount of
speed the hero brings in
as well as the gravity that's applied
during the swing that's going to
accelerate them throughout the swing arc
so due to streaming considerations we
also needed to stay below
about a 10 second average speed of 30
meters per second so that we could avoid
loading stalls and just get everything
in as we're
hurtling through the world so we start
by deciding what our horizontal terminal
velocity is for any given swing
as a baseline this is done by
translating our fall speed into a max
speed while never letting it actually
slow you down so we don't cut your
incoming speed at all
so this ends up feeling pretty natural
to players because they're basically
using gravity to help generate speed
and it helps with streaming because in
order to generate fall speed they have
to be
just falling for a while which is going
to have drag which is going to slow
their horizontal speed
which helps our average speed so once
they're attached we let normal physics
accelerate them up to the max speed and
we go from there
but to enforce that terminal velocity we
do kind of a little bit of a weird thing
we only cap the hero's horizontal speed
and this can have a little bit of an odd
side effect in some cases where you're
actually slowing down in 3d
through the downswing but it does help
you get through these really long
swing arcs a lot faster get down to the
trough get down to where you want to be
in a better way and the slowdown doesn't
come into play too often and most
players are completely unaware it's
happening due to a lot of other speed
cues going on like camera rotation
environment motion motion blur screen
effects everything else that we're just
throwing at them to try and sell
sell that speed now on the other side of
the swing on the upswing
gravity is going to be slowing you down
so however we do have a few things that
we wanted to take into account on this
side of the swing
first we want players to feel like
gravity is appropriately slowing them
down so it needs to feel
physically correct and natural but with
line lengths being highly variable it
creates kind of an inconsistent timing
to the various release levels something
we wanted to try and
kind of close the close the gap on so we
also don't want to slow the player down
too much when they're near the trough we
want to keep
let them keep that hard-earned speed
just a little bit longer so that they
can use it to fling themselves through
the world
and from there we account for all this
by implementing a variable gravity
upswing at any given point on the
upswing your gravity is going to be
determined by a combination of your
current speed
and where you are on the swing arc what
this ends up doing is really helping
swing timing be a lot more consistent
and allowing more swings to move through
the full range of release points so the
player ends up having a much more
predictable time
and can get those high releases even if
they're not necessarily moving that fast
so with the basics out now in place i
want to talk a bit about our experience
of refining the swinging mechanics over
the course of production again we go
back to our usability driven iterative
approach and pro initial goals
we really wanted the player to feel the
momentum in physics but we also wanted
swinging to be accessible
so usability testing proves a critical
element in iterating on this
accessibility this is because developers
quickly become their own worst testers
and i say this all the time to people to
work with because
basically we just know too much about
how things work and we're generally
really quick to forgive ourselves
because our code is amazing and shame on
you for suggesting otherwise
so we also tend to play the game in a
very particular way
the way we designed it real players
however will interact with the game in a
number of unexpected and sometimes
confounding ways stressing elements of
the system that the developer may
never encounter so finally you need to
make sure
functionality lines up with player
expectations as a developer we
may have a perfectly rational
explanation for why something works the
way it does put to a player it just
seems
weird broken confusing or just not any
fun whatsoever
so what do we find well players suck at
managing physics
so forces will often act against their
desires attach points aren't really
directly player driven leading to a lot
of variability
and world geometry is complex and
difficult for many players to
effectively navigate while tethered to
an attach point
the end result was that players felt
that they lacked in they kind of lacked
control over the in-game results
this was despite everything working just
as intended when we made the initial
version of swinging
so how do we approach solving this
problem we injected a number of assists
into swinging to help smooth out the
experience giving them a few less things
to worry about and moving the system's
behavior to be closer to the player
expectations
wherever possible algo our goal was to
keep these as invisible to the players
we could
and we found that if you deviated too
far from real physics players would
notice and often they would react pretty
negatively to it
so our first major usability problem was
that players felt like it was basically
impossible to swing in a straight line
the result of the simulation was
creating a mismatch between the player's
input intent
and the character motion and that and
the results were confusing and
frustrating a lot of our players
so the reason this was happening is that
forces were conspiring to move the
character in a way
that it would settle underneath the
attach point as you might imagine with a
normal pendulum
the tension force has this component
that moves towards the attach point and
gravity just reinforces that to continue
to pull you down
so in this video you'll be able to see
what happens when the tension forces are
in full effect
uh the player is going to be trying to
swing straight down the middle of the
street here
but they're consistently getting pulled
sideways towards the attach point
when they then try and counter steer to
get back to the middle their next
attachment goes on the other side of the
street
and they it just increases frustration
so to top all this off that
zigzagging motion also slows them down
for their straight line speed
and they just feel like they can't
really build up that momentum that
they're looking for
so how do you fight gravity well you
cheat so
we move the simulation pivot away from
the wall
into a position that will help us swing
straighter while leaving the visible
attach point
on the wall we then can blend that pivot
position back
uh back over time or when the player is
turning this makes sure that turns do
pivot on the right place and on the
visible place
and that if you settle underneath the
attach point you're settling under the
visual one not the one that we've moved
away
so this motion was detectable to players
particularly when we a b tested it but
we found that most felden actually
worked more as they expected
aligning their input desire to the
results so in this video you'll see that
pivot tweaking is going to be fully
active
and the player can maintain a lot more
consistent center line and build speed a
lot more easily
and their directional intent is
transferred a lot more cleanly to motion
so the next usability problem was that
players felt they weren't really able to
get a swing line when their body was at
or near the top of a building
this was happening because we required
an attach point to be just a minimum
height above you
and we do that because it prevents you
from just flying over the pivot point or
requiring that we just like slam you
straight down in order to get you under
it
however this rule was completely hidden
from the player and there was not really
any reason though for them to expect or
anticipate that it was there
an additional reason this can occur is
that players perception of the character
position for the world is pretty murky
when they're in the air and all the
buildings are pretty far off to the side
and players are just frankly pretty
impatient when falling and spamming that
r2 button and trying to get a swingline
so what do we do well once a cheater
always a cheater
we secretly allow the simulation attach
point to rise above the building edge
this would raise the valid attach point
ceiling and let people attach a little
bit sooner
it also had this nice side effect of
improving lines that were previously
good but not
really all that great and so player
awareness of this was actually almost
zero it's actually pretty hard to notice
a vertical shift in the pivot point when
you're swinging underneath it
so our next usability problem was our
game director special which is that
players were often over steering when
trying to turn and clipping into the
edges of buildings
and so our solution here is to do a
number of collision tests to scan the
world for problem cases
we send a kona checks forward looking
for things that we might run into so
that we can nudge you just a little to
the left or the right
and we would also send a series of
checks kind of forward and sideways
looking for gaps in upcoming walls this
gave us a clue that we might want to
dampen your steering values a little bit
so that you don't over
steer when trying to make a turn and
slam yourself into the wall instead of
clearing that wall and swinging into the
gap
so these two things combine to give
players a hugely empowering feeling of
just made it without
really noticing that we were the ones
letting them make it
so yet another consistent problem was
that players would often have a line
that was just long enough to smack them
right into the top of a building that
they were that they thought they were
going to clear
and this was kind of particularly bad
because players as we said didn't have
any control over line length
so they were quick to blame us for all
their problems
so the solution then is to just shorten
the line slowly but dynamically in order
to get it
just short enough to clear that building
so we'd use collision to scan ahead for
the maximum height and then we would
slowly raise the player through the
swing until the new line length
was just short enough to clear that
building
so one final element to talk about uh is
how we shorten the line to keep players
above the ground
so we do this because our ground and
rooftops are so littered with cars and
props and pedestrians and squirrels and
other things that trying to navigate and
swing through all that would be
basically impossible
we didn't want players face planing into
the ground all the time and we also
didn't want them becoming just a bug on
a windshield
so similar to clearing buildings we'd
use collision to get the ground tight
and then we'd scale that vertical motion
on their downswing
in order to keep them above the ground
and have kind of a swing floor so that
they could get that nice street sweeping
feel
so once a player's time on the line is
complete it's time for what ends up
being one of the most satisfying
elements of swinging
flinging yourself off the line across
the world with reckless abandon
so when doing so we have two sets of
data for letting go we have releasing
and jumping
jumping gives you a lot more acrobatic
motion higher
a lot more height and more speed but
just simple releasing has simpler
animations and allows you to take a
follow-up action more quickly so
players get to choose between the two
based on what they're trying to do
one of the really nice gameplay features
of swinging when it comes to these
releases is the inherent analog nature
of how release points
translate into exit direction so a
player can choose to release low
to get more speed or hold on just a
little bit longer to get more height
now our first approach to swing releases
was very metric driven
something that was totally sane based on
insomniac's platforming history
so we define a desired jump height and a
time to peak for various release points
and speeds along the swing arc and then
kind of blend those values from those
key from those key points
for any to get one for any release point
the goal was to make jumps feel
predictable and consistent so that
players could plan ahead and get their
next move going
we had this model for about two years
and we were getting mostly positive
feedback on it but there was always this
kind of undercurrent
uh pointing at a lack of player
satisfaction players felt like jumps
were too heavy and that their momentum
on the swingline wasn't really
translating to their jumps
this was because the metric different
approach was changing gravity
significantly for any given release
point
based on player speed to hit that jump
height target that we had set
instead of feeling really rewarding with
an expected amount of fling players kind
of physics feel was being violated
and they felt that they were being
penalized somehow we had this model in
for
the uh helicopter chase demo in 2017
when a lot of people online were saying
oh the swinging looks slow
and so part of that was this kind of
heaviness to the swing
excuse me to the swing jumps so to fix
this
we move to a more free release model
they'll let go of all those controlling
metrics in order to keep a
fixed gravity for each release point
this is the only design factor into the
jump
other than your velocity on the
swingline and as we wanted to remove
anything else that was going to feel
artificial
so once implemented this change created
a much more natural translation of swing
speed to jump size
that better match player expectation we
saw an immediate increase in fun factor
as players were now able to fling
themselves across the world with just
abandon
which led to a greatly increased sense
of speed and joy and just general
cohesiveness of the entire swinging
experience so stepping away from the
simulation side for a minute i want to
talk just a little bit about how the
animation for swinging is implemented on
the code side
this is mostly going to be about the
mechanics of how we pick animations to
play
and then adjust them to more accurately
represent the underlying simulation
so when we first started talking about
swinging the gameplay and animation
groups laid out some high level goals
for how we wanted the animation to look
and feel this included having fluid
animation over the course of the swing
arc
having a clean entry animation from our
air pose through the sling and into the
swing
the character's body obviously wanted to
align to the web line so that it felt
right
and we needed to have this kind of
well-timed kick at the trough in order
to sell momentum
and for a player cue as to where they
were in the swing arc
so our first iteration of animating the
swing we approached the seamless
animation through the swing arc by
actually just using a single animation
the animator created an on-the-line
animation that started at the drop
horizon and went all the way through to
the apex horizon
in code we would then drive the
animation's time based on where the
player was
in the swing arc for any given frame so
in order to get our clean entry
animations we created
separate swing intro animations for
different points along the swing arc
these animations would end pose matched
with the full swing animation so that
the blend of the swing would be seamless
and when a player began a swing we'd we
would calculate where they were in the
swing arc
and blend between those different kind
of pointed animations in order to get
one specifically for that angle
we would then continue to dynamically
blend that value
during the entirety of that intro
animation so that we would get a nice
match
for the final pose of the swing as they
go into that swing animation
in order to get the body uh in order to
get the body to align without having to
make duplicate swing arc animations we
then deployed partial animations to just
kind of adjust the final body angle
we use this on both the body to go side
to side as well as the arms for kind of
a final fix up when those weren't uh
when those weren't matching
so after iterating on this model for
most of production
we had some things that worked just as
expected these included the entry
animation system working really really
well
it allowed smooth entry and timing into
the swing animation
and our adjustment partials did a really
good job at aligning the character to
the swingline with minimal amount of
additional animation required finally
the animation through the swing arc was
fluid
but the system presented a few
limitations that were capping the
animator's creativity
first we had really limited variability
in the swing getting any variation in
this model required animating a brand
new swing from start to finish one end
to the other
and if you wanted to do something
different you had to make another one
and another one and another one
and so next we had very very perceptible
animation time scaling
line lengths and player speeds are
highly variable which was borne out in
highly variable arc speeds
and with a fixed number of animation
frames scaling over a variable time
range
we would get these really easy to feel
time scaling artifacts and this was
especially evident
when we get these really slow sluggish
kick throughs
that lacked any impact whatsoever on
longer lines or slower swings
so we had a couple new goals enable
variety and reduce the time scaling
we accomplished we attacked these by
breaking the swing arc up into pieces
that we then animated separately
we would animate the downswing and the
upswing independently
all the way through the trough which let
us kind of overlap the uh the kick
animation wherever we wanted to kind of
overlap that
inflection point we would then continue
to drive the animation time as before
on the up and down swing animations as
they weren't as susceptible to the
visible scaling as the kicks
as the kick animations were so
once we were in a swing we would
estimate the time to trough uh during
the downswing so that we could trigger
that kick animation at just the right
time
in order to be able to play it at full
speed this instantly made our kicks feel
a lot more powerful and consistent
it also meant that we could plug in a
variety of animations into the kick
portion without needing to reanimate the
rest of the swing
but animators be animators and we
weren't done yet they wanted more
so by breaking the swing animation into
pieces it allowed us to now have a lot
more variety in the way we constructed
the animation for the swing
we were able to introduce custom kicks
and spins with custom upswings we had
hard catch variations of the downswing
and all of these things could be played
with or without one another to get a
whole bunch of
custom a whole bunch of custom swings
and unique swings that look different as
you went from one swing to the next and
add a lot more
texture and flavor to swinging in the
game
so this new iteration helped us solve
our major problems by allowing us to
create a lot more animation variety and
it also helped us eliminate the
animation scaling for the most notable
portion of the swing
so one final problem worth noting was
that with all of the various moves that
spider-man can do he would often end up
in poses
that didn't really play nicely with our
swing intro animations
we needed to either wait for the
animation to get to a point where the
character could blend
into the intro better or live with
really really bad looking blends as we
tried to get into those sling animations
so to solve this animation wanted to add
a lot more variety to swing intros
but programming didn't really want to
manage each of those clips manually
so to push that work over to the content
creators we added a data driven setup
that allowed animators to tell the game
what the next animation would be
from the current time in the active
animation they'd mark up the section of
a jump animation with data that would
point to custom slinging animations
and this allowed them to cleanly get of
all these out of all these crazy
acrobatic poses
with custom slings that made the
traversal feel a lot more seamless and
the character feel a lot more dynamic
so kind of stepping away now from
animation i want to talk a bit about our
approach to the traversal camera
we knew from previous games that good
motion and animation only goes so far in
translating the experience to the player
the camera is actually often most the
most important aspect and conveying
elements of speed and translation
in a way that gives the player that kind
of visceral connection to the action
that's on the screen
so when we started out our top level
goals for the traversal camera
we came up with three main items that we
found important after early prototyping
with kind of a mostly static camera
first we wanted to minimize the amount
of player input was required
this is because players would often need
to be using the face buttons and we
didn't want to require them to have to
switch between that and the stick input
that was just a lot of camera management
that we didn't want people to mess with
next we needed to accentuate the
pendulum motion and the forces on the
line
and finally we wanted to communicate a
sense of speed to the player
so we have a pretty long history of
third-person games at insomniac and
we've generally started with a follow
camera model that tries to have the
camera looking
in the same direction as the hero's
velocity so while successful in other
games
in other contexts it did present a few
problems for spider-man particularly
with
at the high speeds that spider-man could
move and how much we had to let you see
where you were going
so the biggest issue was that when we
tuned it effectively
um you you were to where you were going
it was extremely susceptible to these
sudden these sudden changes in velocity
causing large changes in view direction
the camera just swing around
incessantly on people this had this
feedback loop with camera relative
controls where the camera would change a
lot which would change your input a lot
change your camera a lot and you just
get into this death spiral
so in order to fix the problem we move
to a model based on the player more
dragging the camera around this was done
by we'd predict the player's position
based on their current speed and then
we'd use that to calculate how it would
drag
more of a camera boom and how that would
change the rotation
this ended up being a lot less noisy
with velocity changes as the frame of it
as the frame to frame delta was
generally a whole lot smaller
so with the camera now following us more
appropriately i want to talk a bit about
how we accentuate the pendulum motion
on the of the player through camera
motion in addition to just
feeling better this also actually helped
address two major usability issues
that a more stan more static camera was
presenting
first as stated before players weren't
really noticing the full extent of
vertical translation the character was
actually performing
players were also presenting a really
poor level of comprehension of where
they
actually were in the swing arc they were
frequently hanging on for too long
releasing high
losing all the forward momentum and
wondering when the hell happened
so the first thing we manipulate to help
sell the swing arc is the camera's pitch
we try and roughly match uh the swing
arcs pitch in order to feel that motion
through the camera as you can see here
we want to keep the pitch a little more
flattened off
on the downswing so that you can keep
your eyes on the horizon and keep an eye
on where you're going
and then on the upswing we tend to
exaggerate the pitch a little bit
in order to communicate that rise more
effectively and let them feel like
they're moving up without getting too
far into the upswing
so the next element we added to help the
player feel the swing arc more was to
move the character's position and screen
space down and then
back up over the course of the swing
this created kind of a real world
physical tracking response from the
player
that would reinforce the in-game motion
as they kind of looked down and looked
up with the player with the character
moving on screen
so when it came to turning we really
wanted to get that get players to feel
that they were kind of whipping around a
corner at high speed
and bringing that same sensation you get
when you're kind of in a turning car
leading to the side
and to get this effect we apply a little
bit of roll to the camera when turning
and scale it based on the line angle and
turn speed
but a word of caution here we did have
to be careful not to push it too far due
to motion sickness concerns
we did add an option to scale it down or
turn it off entirely for people that had
problems with that so now that we have
players feeling the translation and
traversal we need to make sure that they
actually felt the speed
so this means we needed to layer as many
visual cues as possible to help
sell not just the current speed but
changes in speed
probably the most impactful thing to
sensing speed through the world is going
to be field of view
a wider field of view tends to elongate
objects in front of you making it feel
like you're covering more ground
and it also brings a lot of peripheral
objects into view that are going to be
moving
really fast by you so you get a lot more
of that relative motion feel
in order to really sell the changes in
speed we're constantly updating the
game's field of view while traversing
to deal with sudden speed changes we
rely more on actually adjusting the
camera's follow distance as
you don't want to bounce field of view
around too much it gets really weird um
we have certain kind of explosive moves
that create a spring action on the
camera so that it falls back
before blending closer again this gives
those moves much bigger sense of impact
like the characters boosting away
suddenly leaving the camera in the dust
and then it has to play catch up a
little bit
so here you'll be able to see all that
coming together to show the sense of
speed
there's a little bit of depot here on
the side to give you a better idea of
how the field of view and follow
distance are changing as it goes through
the action
good
all right so the final bit of camera
development i want to talk about
is related to how the camera is handled
when we perform a variety of traversal
moves
so our first version of the traversal
camera treated each move as its kind of
special
unique item this was driven by a desire
to make every move as cinematic as
possible with the thought that if you
string together a bunch of really
cinematic moves you're going to get
something extra special super cinematic
this presented a couple of problems
though in this video
from an early vertical slice you'll see
some of the issues with the everything
as a special snowflake
and how that kind of breaks down you'll
see that going from move to move
would cause a change in framing and
field of view that could kind of muddle
the perception of speed
and rapid sequencing of moves would
create a very noisy relationship between
the world the character and the view
so how do we get better well we started
with a more unified model for our all of
our traversal moves that had a speed
driven field of view and follow distance
that would stay consistent across all of
the different moves
we also smoothed out any adjustments we
were doing to offsets to make those
changes feel less aggressive and
not kind of upset the player so here
you're gonna see that we got ended up
getting some pretty good results
uh you're gonna get a lot more
consistent perception of speed when
moving from one move to another
the camera ends up being a lot more
predictable to the player and one move
flows into the next without
feeling like there's a major state
change that the player has to suddenly
adjust to
this proved a lot more fun and
predictable to players and gave an
overall better experience
all right so as we started to get a full
set of traversal moves in the game and
playing with them more both internally
and through usability we found that
unsurprisingly our first version was
rarely good enough
so this led to a lot of feedback that
motion felt stiff and imprecise
players weren't able to navigate as well
as they wanted a lot of moves weren't
matching expectations
and they were unable to actually land
where they wanted to so we started kind
of revisiting things
so with wall run our first pass was set
up to actually be locked to either be
horizontal or vertical with no
in between and no ability to switch the
entry was based on a combination of
character velocity
input direction the walls facing and it
had a heavy bias towards maintaining
your current momentum
so if you're going really fast
horizontally you are really likely to
get a horizontal wall run
the single biggest problem we had was
that wall run entry direction was really
poorly mapped to player expectations
they never really understood the concept
of momentum driving the entry direction
and how that overwhelmed their input
this was made even worse because there
was just no ability to switch from
horizontal to vertical
if they didn't get what they wanted and
on top of that the camera direction
versus a vertical wall
was making input to entry mapping even
more confusing
can you tell me in this image pushing up
on the stick is that supposed to make
you go
forward or up a lot of players had
didn't really know what they wanted to
do in that situation
so players would often try to compensate
for this by pointing the camera where
they wanted to go
but the system was paying zero attention
to the camera and so it wasn't helping
them
so with our big problems identified we
set out to make some changes
the first thing we did was to add analog
steering this created a lot more
in-between values for entry direction
as well as giving players the ability to
adjust on the fly if they weren't happy
with their entry direction
then we revisited our entry direction
process as a whole we added a
camera-driven influence to help players
uh to help translate player intent to
in-game results and we then
significantly amped up the effect of
player input over momentum so that they
had a lot more control over the results
and what happened get on the output
so these combined to result in a
significant reduction in player
frustration
so for in-air control once they're off
the line just flying through the air
we wanted the player to have an initial
or we had an initial approach that
heavily flavored momentum again we were
looking at that momentum thing over and
over again in the first rev
so this meant that in air steering was
fairly stiff and players needed to rely
on web moves like webs
like swinging and web zip for rapid
direction change the idea was that would
make your swing releases more meaningful
and consequential
but this model presented a number of
problems in play testing much like
everything else seems to
the first first swing speeds amplify
small differences in angle
over large over large distances this
made it almost impossible to be precise
if you
if you tried to release off a line and
you saw something in the distance little
variations in that angle would cause
big variations in where you ended up in
addition
players were really just terrible at
thinking ahead to manage their speed
while there are tools to slow down they
generally go as
fast as possible to their destination
and only once they're there do they try
and stop
this usually ends up with the player
kind of fumbling around and orbiting
their destination as they try and get
closer and just having a bad time
so finally players were having a lot of
difficulty reacting quickly to changes
in situation or
geometry so in order to help solve these
problems we had to put more control
back in players hands and let go of some
of our really strict momentum-based
concepts
to start we significantly increased the
nr turn speeds this immediately helped
players react a lot more quickly to
dynamic elements
and it also allowed people to more
effectively set up their next move
increasing their ability to chain moves
and just basically use the full suite of
traversal elements
later on we massively increase the
amount of drag applied to the
to the player when pulling back on the
stick this let players feel a lot more
precise when they were reaching their
destination because they could go from
60 to zero in a very short time
overall this led to a lot fewer
instances of players fumbling around
their destination and let people feel
like they could kind of stick the
landing
so the next thing we need to address uh
from specific was our
more specific world interaction moves so
when we started making the game
we knew that we wanted to make the city
feel like a big part of traversal
and spider-man's interaction with the
world needed to be tangible
and while swinging and web zip did
require geometry to work
you were still kind of mid-air and
disconnected when using them we wanted
something that was a little more tactile
so our first version was zipping through
the legs of a water tower with our web
tunnel move
this was really cinematic from a
presentation standpoint and it really
fulfilled the fantasy of interacting
with those specific objects
but it did have a few shortcomings the
first problem is that the move has a
pretty rigid directionality
there wasn't a lot of room for players
to modify the direction going through
the object because it was
a fixed structure and in addition the
entry angles were pretty limited you
could only engage the web tunnel from a
limited angle range
before it started to look really weird
of kind of getting sucked in sideways
and turning through this thing
so in this case we recognize that web
tunnel had some inherent limitations
that we weren't going to be able to get
over
in addition we like to have we liked
having the move as it was for certain
situations that cinematic presentation
was really effective for certain things
so instead we created point launch a
move where you could zip to a point on
top of an object and then spring back
off instantly with a big jump
we were able to get the desired world
interaction we were looking for with web
tunnels along with a number of
additional benefits
first the player could enter and exit a
point launch from any direction
and because we needed just a point the
opportunity for placement in the world
had
increased dramatically so once point
launch was implemented we started to
notice that we had a lot of traversal
moves that were treating
that we were treating as unique we had
new names for them and we thought they
were all special but to the player they
all felt like the same thing in this
case that was
go to a thing so as you can see we had
separate unique button combinations for
going to a perch point launching and
zipping to a wall
to make things worse point launch only
worked on perches
which were a special kind of point but
we had a very similar move that worked
on perches and edges
and ultimately this led to a lot of
problems with the player's ability to
kind of mentally map these for this
variety of controls to what felt to them
like the same action so they'd fumble a
lot to the wrong thing
and just generally get themselves
screwed up so our solution was then to
merge
all of this into a single input space
using the triggers
this helped to ensure that the button to
action mapping in the player's brain was
a lot more one-to-one
however it's not just a matter of
merging buttons it's never that simple
it did require us to adapt some of the
moves as well
first we expanded point launch to work
on all edges uh which ended up being a
win for the player and we merged it with
zip to perch
we then moves it to wall to be an a-mode
only action so that its targeting didn't
conflict with the other moves that it
was sharing buttons with
so after iterating our controls by doing
things like changing buttons and adding
moves
there's a few major takeaways from this
section that i feel are pretty important
uh first if the player expectation and
system designs are not aligned then your
controls just fail and the player
experience is going to drop
we spent a lot of time giving
long-winded design reasons why our
controls were the way they were
when they started but ultimately players
will just never get the most out of a
system that they have trouble using
and the next lesson would be that trying
to add analog input and behavior to our
moves
helped add depth utility freedom and
flow to our moves and just increase the
players experience
so as we were getting towards the end of
production and our core mechanics were
all in place we started to drive down
to the next level of usability feedback
we found that players were still
feeling that the experience had a
somewhat kind of stuttery rhythm
where it would feel incredibly smooth at
times but they were kind of consistently
getting these little snags and hiccups
that were breaking their momentum
so as we kept gathering information we
found that most of the problems boiled
down to just a few cases across the city
in response we created a kind of small
palette of moves that would help
maintain flow to get around those rough
edges
many of these moves were designed to be
a natural extension from the character's
current action
so they didn't require any input one of
the players who feel like they were
expertly executing these moves that
would often require unnatural reflexes
if they wanted to execute them manually
so my first example here shows one of
our biggest issues
you'd kind of clip a corner causing a
short wall run that would then eject you
sideways
the sudden change in direction would
often surprise players and would frankly
frequently create situations that were
difficult to recover from
as they were kind of exiting at a high
enough velocity they'd often get clear
across the street before they knew what
the hell happened to them
so we kind of fixed this by adding just
a small little move to redirect you
parallel
to your incoming velocity if you were
only wall running for a really short
time
this very quickly got the player back in
action with a consistent reference
direction and they were able to just
get right back to what they were doing
so the next example looks more at a case
where players didn't really have a tool
to change direction easily
if a player was wall running up a
building and wanted to corner over it
they would have to clear the building
and then figure out what their next move
was once they could actually see what
was above them
this led to kind of this gap in flow
while players processed that view
and caused a lot of stall for them
to fix this we added a move that the
player could trigger before clearing the
wall
to get over the edge and redirect their
velocity all in one shot this added a
little layer of skill which was nice
and it added some depth while letting
players a lot more efficiently navigate
over these buildings
so a lot of our additional moves
centered around trying to traverse
through space
near walls and how that conflicts with
our art team's desire to have a lot of
stuff sticking out of those walls and
into our play space
the biggest factor here was fire escapes
it just didn't feel like new york
without them but they were basically the
total arch nemesis for the traversal
team
the entire production we ended up making
a lot of vaulting moves both from the
air and from wall run and from swing
to get around these as well as
completely custom ladder climbing web
move to kind of
climb them like a ladder up a fire
escape stack we also needed to deal with
signs hanging out of buildings
particularly in places like chinatown
and a lot of small little outcroppings
and changes in wall contour
that were too small to just wall run
over but they were too
big to just wall run over but too small
to actually run on
entirely so and today that wraps up our
journey that we went on with creating
traversal for marvel spider-man
we had a whole lot of fun along the way
working with such a great character but
there are definitely a few
key things i believe any developer can
learn from our experience here
first when creating mechanics start with
a simple implementation
and then add complexity only as you
uncover new problems
by keeping things simple early we were
able to avoid going too far down a path
that our players wouldn't respond to
which in many cases
kept us from wasting work we ended up
with a system that had a whole lot of
features
but many of the additions were things
that we could never have anticipated
needing or wanting ahead of time
second you have to stay flexible in your
approach to creating mechanics we were
initially really resistant to some of
the best changes because we had all the
design reasons listed out why it was
working like it was supposed to
and clearly it was the feedback that was
a problem by allowing the game to evolve
we came to a final product that was far
superior to what we thought was the
right approach
earlier in development and finally you
are your own worst tester and in some
cases the rest of your dev team quickly
catches up with being terrible
developers know exactly how their
systems work and they're just
and they're in the way they're supposed
to be used so when you play the game it
will often work exactly as you expected
different players will play the game in
wildly different ways and you'll never
know where the real problems and edge
cases are until you let them loosen your
game
even with external play testers you
should always challenge yourself
and others to try to play the game in
different ways and try and have a
different experience with the
mapping what your controls are into the
game
so that's it for me thanks so much for
coming
and it looks like we've got about 10
minutes for some q a
gonna start over here hello uh so the
problem space you're working in seemed
like it required like a ton of different
skill sets to effectively solve these
problems like cinematography
physics game design you know a whole
bunch of others how did you
what was like the composition of your
team like and how did you kind of
effectively organize around these
different skill sets to solve these
problems
so um we had what we call the traversal
pod which consisted of
a couple of programmers a handful of
animators a designer
as well as just everybody else looking
at traversal in general so we'd have
effects people that would come in and
help with effects
our animation director would also kind
of be looking at things from a
cinematography standpoint as well as our
you know the animators in the traversal
pod and so it was really just getting it
was an
extremely collaborative environment and
getting all the different people from
all the different disciplines with
eyeballs on it and everybody looking for
ways to give input on how to improve
things
thanks
i was it any uh inspiration draw from
spider-man 2's web slinging
mechanics uh i mean we early on we
definitely played all of the games
um you know spider-man 2 did a lot of
really great things so did ultimate
spider-man so did web of shadows so did
asm ii
like those were all teams that had a lot
of really great ideas
that they executed in different ways and
so um we definitely took things from
them there was definitely that sense of
you know
the biggest thing we got through the
history of spider-man games was your
webs better darn well attached to
buildings
but when we took it from there we ended
up at the end of the day wanting to make
something that was also kind of our own
and i think we sort of hit that by
having a traversal system that layered a
lot of different moves together
to make you feel like you had a wider
palate thank you
um what were some of the challenges and
solutions you had
with um swing heavy combat situations
such as like the final
doc ock fight which was on a rooftop
yeah
so that created kind of a lot of weird
things and we actually had the ability
to
basically have a config data set
that kind of parameterized how swinging
worked and so one of the things we were
able to do was make a duplicate data set
that was entirely reparameterized for
different situations
so when we were inside gct inside grand
central or when we were in a combat
arena like a boss fight
we could sit there and basically just
change all the parameters for how
swinging worked in order to make it fit
that space a little bit better we didn't
want to deviate too far we needed to be
kind of make sense to the player
but it did let us make sure that we
weren't kind of overshooting things when
you weren't getting um
when you're outside it's these big huge
swings that give you a lot of height and
a lot of stuff like that if you're
inside or in a boss arena
that becomes a problem if you're
constantly getting yourself flung up in
the air with nothing to swing from and
just have to free fall for a while so
um that re-parameterization really
helped us to make things
fit whatever situation we were dealing
with thank you
hi uh thanks for the talk really really
excellent
um so i have a question about
uh what you said earlier where you would
do animation blending to correct the way
spider-man was facing
during uh swing but with all of his cool
poses and so on
how did you prevent that blend from
creating like
strange artifacts during the animation
uh i mean
i'll give a lot of credit there to our
animation team with uh elliot grossman
who did a lot of the animation work and
to our core engine
programmer for animation johnny garrett
they made a sweet animation system and a
bunch of sweet animations that did a
really cool stuff
for the most part the blending ended up
we just made sure to kind of control
where those things go
and we made sure to control when we use
them so that they didn't get too far
outside of what we needed
we also had the side effect that when
you're swinging you're kind of out in
the air so
unlike if you're on the ground or
somewhere where you have to really kind
of hand plant on things and touch things
if there was a little bit of drift from
those partials and stuff it didn't
really matter as much
for swinging and so it gave us a lot
more freedom to kind of play with that
stuff we just had to make sure that
visually you were lined up with the line
and it felt like those forces were
correct
and at that point we were good to go all
right thanks
hey um it seems like throughout
development you're changing like gravity
settings adding new mechanics that
spider-man can use
how did you like work alongside the
level design team like during this
process to make sure that
all their work isn't like thrown away as
soon as you change like a huge
fundamental setting or something
that was one of the biggest challenges
we had um
you know working on not necessarily a
new ip
new ip to us um we didn't really have
all the mechanics locked down
until part you know we were well into
production before things started to get
locked down which as you said creates
challenges for
the design team a lot of it came down to
the design mirror in our pod josue
basically did a lot of work of trying to
maintain things consistently he actually
built the metrics for the entire city
by himself and then it was done and then
we actually generated geometry after
that through houdini so
we got a lot of consistency in the open
world by just having that go through one
person
for interiors and stuff we just tried to
set up some metrics and
go from there i would say that kind of
swinging on interiors is something that
i think
we didn't make as good as we would have
liked because it was such a it was such
a big move and we didn't have the time
to
really focus on that but we were able to
use that reparameterization
to make it work for most of the spaces
that we needed it awesome
hi uh excellent talk thank you so much
great game definitely stealing all your
math
uh i noticed that uh in this talk about
traversal you didn't really talk about
the wall climbing at all
like walking around i'm assuming it
might have either been outside the scope
but this talk are not super relevant but
um that's a system that i've actually
messed around with uh for my own game
and i'm curious if it was ever supposed
to be a
sort of a bigger element of reversal
than it was and then you clamped it
because it was too complicated
or any edge cases like that um so wall
crawl was really you know it's really
identifiable with the character
but it has this um it has this problem
for games
which is when you do it you can only go
so fast or you look like a weird
salamander
um and usually when people are on a wall
they
want to interact out from the wall
there's nowhere to put your camera
except for inside of you or something
and so it creates a lot of these
gameplay problems our designers
in some ways had trouble figuring out
even how to use it um
our buildings had a lot of complexity to
their geometry that added a lot of
a lot of complexity to the wall crawl
stuff we actually had uh ross mckintosh
one of our programmers was working on it
for
um probably a couple years working on
some wall crawl stuff and
you know it's it's like it's a really
really complicated problem to deal with
all of that geometry
i noticed that you like hard clamped it
to go around corners of specific
animations so it didn't actually have to
deal with like artifacts and stuff yeah
so we tried to kind of scope down in
places where we could to make to
take some things that were really hard
problems and make them into um
a little bit simpler problems and so we
we did that
wherever we could with wall crawl we
tried we still wanted to make sure and
fulfill that kind of fantasy element
while having most of the game focused on
this
big fast speed traversal and so we just
chose to
have wall crawl be something that we you
know implemented as well as we could
but didn't try to over focus on makes
sense thank you so much
hey um amazing talk um totally loved it
uh we have
we tried to build a spider-man game as
one of our prototypes and we really
really failed to
do it um so one of the things i handed
out about was you mentioned that
we use used box volumes for collision
detections and that
so how did you decide which objects in
the scene you'd go to was it like
applied to everything that he could
attach to and if so how did you maintain
the performance
as to where you detect the collision
occurs does it happen
in a particular area and how so so is
sorry
uh was your question like how do we
decide where to place markup and where
not to
yeah uh so for the most part we wanted
to in the in the open world we marked up
everything uh we like i was saying we
used our procedurally generating
uh system houdini well it's not ours
it's middleware that we license but
um to place a lot of that stuff so it
was kind of everywhere
um for interiors and things we would
just decide if the space was in metric
and we would
place or not place things based on
whether it was in metric for that
um and other than that we would just
find other things that we wanted to
attach to like tree tops and stuff like
that and just place mark up there that's
where we could use our prefabs to say
okay this object is always going to come
bundled with this markup so every time
it gets out there it's populated with
that markup so
it really just came down to anything
that as much as possible anything that
looked like you should be able to swing
from it we tried to get markup on it um
do you have any performance issues in
trying to find out which place to attach
to or like whether anything you have to
optimize
uh we had a few things we went through a
number of iterations on
um on that we ended up getting better by
like i said like using kind of a sphere
database and some search query
um to kind of pack all the data in as
much as we could
um really helped us kind of speed things
up we ended up being able to move it off
onto a job on
kind of another thread so that it could
happen in the background and so it ended
up taking even in an area that was
highly dense it ended up taking
on the ps4 probably in a dense area
about two milliseconds to process and
chug through everything so it wasn't
necessarily cheap
but it didn't get it wasn't too
untractable either cool thank you
hi thank you for your impressive
sessions
so i'm making a swinging player game
and like a spiderman so if you
will make the real spiderman so what do
you
change spec war game design
what was your question sorry i didn't
sorry so so what do you
change for boyer game
like spiderman what do we kind of change
to make a game like spider-man
uh so go through the
town and uh swing
with rope so
so is it kind of how do we have to
change the city to make swinging work
yeah yeah you're right
gotcha okay so it's actually interesting
we had a lot of tests early on
talking about how um how wide the
streets needed to be
if you actually take full new york with
streets they're actually really terrible
for swinging because your line angles
end up being like too far to the side
so we did a lot of tests to figure out
what the right widths were for the
streets
a lot of metric tests early on and so we
had to kind of play around with all of
that really early
in order to find what the right
distances were before we kind of
populated the entire city with stuff so
it was kind of just progressing things a
little bit
a little bit at a time in lockstep as we
were kind of iterating on the design
side and on the world construction side
and iterating on the swing side to make
sure those two things kind of work
together in a really nice way
thank you cool
there's other questions all right i
think we're out of time thanks guys